Guide to the Thomas Wells Farnam Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Thomas Wells Farnam papers
1918-1945
1918-1919
MS 659
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
4
(5 boxes, 1 folio)
Correspondence, cablegrams, reports, notes, and other papers of Thomas W. Farnam, financier and administrator. These papers relate to Farnam's service in Serbia, 1918-1919, as American Red Cross Commissioner in charge of relief and hospitals following World War I.
Farnam, Thomas Wells, 1877-1943
Arrangement
Arranged in five series: I. General Correspondence. II. Cables. III. Progress and Other Operational Reports. IV. Miscellaneous Operational and Administrative Memoranda and Notes. V. Personal and Memorabilia.
Biographical / Historical
Thomas Wells Farnam was born in Litchfield, Connecticut. He attended Milton and Hotchkiss and received his B. A. from Yale in 1899. Between 1901 and 1917 he was involved in various banking and investment enterprises in New Haven. Immediately following the American declaration of war against Germany Farnam was appointed Associate Director (he subsequently became Director) of the American Red Cross Supply Service in Washington, D. C. From October 1917 to September 1918 he served as Assistant United States Food Administrator for the state of Connecticut. Farnam was then appointed American Red Cross Commissioner to Serbia in charge of relief and hospitals, carrying the assimilated rank of Lieutenant Colonel: he was posted to Belgrade where he remained through the middle of 1919. After the signing of the treaty of Versailles Farnam returned to New Haven, and he devoted the remaining years of his life to Yale University administrative affairs. He served, in turn, as Alumni Fellow of the Yale Corporation (1919-1922), Acting Secretary of the university (1920-1923), Associate Treasurer, and Comptroller (1921-1943). He died in 1943.
Scope and Contents
The T. W. Farnam Papers comprise those materials which relate to Farnam's service in Serbia during 1918-1919. They are arranged in five series, as follows:
(I) General Correspondence (1918-1919). (1 box) [arranged alphabetically by correspondent]
(II) Cablegrams. (1 box) Copies of official cables from Washington, Paris, and Rome.
(III) Progress (and other operational) Reports. (1 box) Copies of progress reports from various Yugoslav regions by members of the American Mission, and drafts of the "Final Report" of June 1919.
(IV) Miscellaneous Operational and Administrative Memoranda and Notes. (1 box) [arranged alphabetically by topical subdivisions]
(V) Personal and Memorabilia. (1 box and 1 oversize portfolio) Farnam's "Diary", covering the period January - June 1919; copies of correspondence of Harry W. Frantz and Cornelia Reese concerning Thomas W. Farnam, 1944-1945; miscellaneous photographs taken in Serbia; and citations, warrants and diplomas.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
World War, 1914-1918; Serbia; United States -- Foreign relations; Health services administrators; Anderson, Henry W. (Henry Watkins), 1870-; Dodge, Henry Percival, 1870-1936; Farnam, Thomas Wells, 1877-1943; Farrand, Livingston, 1867-1939; Hoffman, Marvina, 1887-1966; Scoville, Herbert, 1877-1937; Treadwell, George Curtis, 1872-1932; Wells, H. Gideon (Harry Gideon), 1875-1943; American National Red Cross; Yale University -- Officals and employees
- General correspondence, 1918-1919; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  The number of items are contained in parentheses before the unitdate.
  - Agriculture, Acting Serbian Minister of (3) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Anderson, Henry W. (3), 1919 March (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Anderson, Henry W. (19), 1919 April-June (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Anderson, Henry W. (48), 1918 December-1919 February (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Armstrong, H. F. (3) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Aupperle, D. W. (1) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Aupperle, H. V. (11) (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bakewell, C. M. (1) (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Barry, Stella (1) (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bender, L. R. (1) (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Bicknell, E. P. (5) (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Borissavljevitch, Colonel (2) (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Boscovic, Colonel (1) (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Boudimirovitch, Jivoin (1) (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Bradford, Alice (1) (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Bradner, M. R. (1) (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Burr, G. H. (1) (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Capps, Edward (1) (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Carey, J. P. (36) (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Colby, F. T. (1) (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Conner, C. H. (3) (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Corey, Herbert (1) (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Corcoran, Joan M. (2) (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Curtis, F. H. (4) (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Davison, Henry (2) (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Denison, R. C. (1) (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Dodge, Geoffrey (1) (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Dodge, H. Percival (7) (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Doornbos, G. T. (2) (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Duncan, R. F. (1) (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Edwards, G. H. (2) (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Emerson, F. L. (1) (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Farnam, H. W. (1) (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Farrand, Livingston (2) (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Fortescue, C. G. (2) (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Frantz, Harry (8) (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Frothingham, J. W. (5) (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Gibson, H. D. (1) (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Grouitch, Darinka (2) (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Hamlen, J. R. (1) (Box 1, Folder 39A)
  - Hargis, L. D. (5) (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Hay, H. S. (1) (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Hoffman, Malvina (3) (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Hunter, E. (1) (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Jager, John (1) (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - James, C. L. (1) (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Johnston, Beatrice (3) (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Jovanovich, N. (1) (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Korac, M. (3) (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Koroshetz (2) (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Kovesty (?), D. (1) (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Lewis, Clara (5) (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Lieneman, J. E. (1) (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - McAlevy, George W. (1) (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - McCarthy, D. J. (1) (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Martini, Iride (2) (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Milutinóvic, Bor. (1) (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Morgan, Harjes and Company (2) (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Olds, Robert E. (2) (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - O'Neill, M. A. (1) (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Orr, Gertrude (1) (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Owsley, J. E. (1) (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Perkins, R. H. (4) (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Persons, R. F. (1) (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Plunkett, E. A. (1) (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Pribicevic, Milan (6) (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Prince, Morton (1) (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Puranovic, W. L. (2) (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Rachitch, M. (4) (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Ramsey, H. W. (1) (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - de Reinach, H. de (1) (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Ross, Donald (2) (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Ryan, W. B. (1) (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Saxton, Stella (1) (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Schell, E. A. (1) (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - Scoville, Herbert (3) (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Seidemann, H. P. (2) (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - Society for the Protection of Yugoslav Children (1) (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - Solarovitsch, Danisa (3) (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - Stoddard, Louis E. (6) (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - de Tarnowsky, George (2) (Box 1, Folder 80)
  - Thwaits, F. C. (2) (Box 1, Folder 81)
  - Tontzakovitch, Lepa (1) (Box 1, Folder 82)
  - Treadwell, Geo. C. (1) (Box 1, Folder 83)
  - Trowbridge, E. C. T. (3) (Box 1, Folder 84)
  - Ullman, I. M. (2) (Box 1, Folder 85)
  - Wadsworth, Eliot (5) (Box 1, Folder 86)
  - Wells, H. G. (1) (Box 1, Folder 87)
  - Wheeler, James E. (1) (Box 1, Folder 87A)
  - Wilsey, Marietta (1) (Box 1, Folder 88)
  - Wishard, D. M. (1) (Box 1, Folder 89)
  - Woodard, C. B. (1) (Box 1, Folder 90)
- Cables, 1918-1919; Series II
  - Washington and Paris, 1918 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Rome and miscellaneous, 1918-1919 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Progress (and other operational) reports, Circa 1919; Series III
  - Preliminary memorandum on Serbia, 1919 January 22 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Progress Reports (Captain Buck) (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Progress Reports (Major Carey) (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Progress Reports (Captain Edwards) (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Progress Reports (Miscellaneous - Southern Serbia) (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - "Memorandum re: Work in Serbia", 1919 June (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - "Final Report": Outlines, 1919 June (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - "Final Report" [with map], 1919 June 30 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Miscellaneous operational and administrative memoranda and notes, Circa 1918; Series IV
  - re: Children's Relief (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - re: Civil Relief (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - re: Community House, Belgrade (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - re: Cooperatives (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - re: Financial Accounts (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - re: Food Supplies (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - re: Honors Received by Mission (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - re: Inventories (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - re: Medical/Artificial Limb Department (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - re: Medical/Hospitals and Orphanages (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - re: Medical/Public Health Plan (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - re: Medical/Tuberculosis Program (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - re: Organizational and Personnel (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - re: Press Releases (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - re: Schools (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - re: Workrooms, Belgrade (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Personal and memoranda, Circa 1918-1945; Series V
  - Diary
    - 1919 January-March (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - 1919 April-June (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Photographs (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Copies of correspondence of Harry W. Frantz and Cornelia Reese concerning Thomas W. Farnam, 1944 September 15, 1945 January 27, February 5 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Diplomas, warrants, and citations (Box 6)